<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-05T23:05:09+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Just Sustainability Design Lab</title><entry><title type="html">Post-growth Human–Computer Interaction: 21st Century Information Technologies for Life Beyond the Polycrisis</title><link href="/2026/02/05/post-growth-hci-repfp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post-growth Human–Computer Interaction: 21st Century Information Technologies for Life Beyond the Polycrisis" /><published>2026-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2026/02/05/post-growth-hci-repfp</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2026/02/05/post-growth-hci-repfp.html"><![CDATA[<p>The <strong>Research Excellence Postdoctoral Fellows Program</strong> at the University of Toronto is a prestigious opportunity for early-career scholars to develop and expand their research expertise at one of the world’s most distinguished public research universities. The Program, a collaborative initiative between the University and its divisions, is designed to engage 100 exceptional postdoctoral fellows across the university over the next few years. Its goal is to attract the highest-quality researchers globally—top domestic and international emerging scholars who demonstrate exceptional promise in their fields and the potential to have a positive impact at U of T.</p>

<p>Candidates interested in holding the fellowship at the Faculty of Information should first review the descriptions of available opportunities on the <a href="https://ischool.utoronto.ca/award/research-excellence-postdoctoral-fellows-program/">Faculty of Information website</a>. They should then contact the listed supervisor—and co-supervisor, if applicable—to discuss the possibility of working together on the final application, due <strong>April 1</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="research-theme">Research Theme</h2>
<p><strong>Post-growth Human–Computer Interaction: 21st Century Information Technologies for Life Beyond the Polycrisis</strong><br />
<strong>Supervisor:</strong> <a href="https://ischool.utoronto.ca/faculty-profile/christoph-becker/">Christoph Becker</a></p>

<p>As our world’s linked ecological and social crises deepen, the intensifying risks of climate and social collapse ask us how we intend to relate to the rest of nature, the planet, and each other. The science is clear: on a finite planet, the expansion of material activity we know as “economic growth” is ending. The ecological response is “post-growth”: to equitably transform our socio-economic systems to overcome their growth addiction. Post-growth is gaining traction.</p>

<p>This fellowship asks: <strong>How does a post-growth world change what we consider “good” information technology?</strong> Today’s technologies are shaped by our societies’ addiction to unsustainable extractive accumulation. But alternative visions, theories, organizations, practices, and technologies already exist. Alternative social media and worker-owned tech co-ops center principles of care, community, and mutual aid; digital commons are collectively governed in global infrastructures to support local production and repair. The emergent field of post-growth computing prioritizes sufficiency over efficiency, repairability over obsolescence, conviviality over convenience, commoning over commodification, care over control, autonomy over automation, and relationality over separability.</p>

<p>This fellowship centers these values and develops pathways for post-growth computing, asking questions such as:</p>

<ol>
  <li>How do organizational structures support and constrain ecological and relational responsibilities in post-growth technology development?</li>
  <li>What if we build technology that centers sufficiency, care, conviviality, and cooperation? How do these values materialize socio-technically?</li>
  <li>What notions of scalability are appropriate to post-growth?</li>
</ol>

<p>The fellow will join a growing global network of communities and researchers who envision and build emerging convivial technologies for resilience, care, and cooperation.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="learn-more-about-the-fellowship">Learn more about the fellowship</h2>

<p>Find more information on the <a href="https://ischool.utoronto.ca/award/research-excellence-postdoctoral-fellows-program/">Faculty of Information website</a>.</p>

<p>For questions about the application process at the Faculty of Information, please contact<br />
<a href="mailto:research.ischool@utoronto.ca">research.ischool@utoronto.ca</a></p>

<p><strong>Interested in this research theme?</strong><br />
If you are interested in <em>Post-growth Human–Computer Interaction: 21st Century Information Technologies for Life Beyond the Polycrisis</em>, contact <a href="mailto:christoph.becker@utoronto.ca"><strong>Prof. Christoph Becker</strong></a> to discuss project ideas and fit with the fellowship before applying.</p>]]></content><author><name>cristian-velasquez</name></author><category term="opportunity" /><category term="fellowship" /><category term="postdoc" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Research Excellence Postdoctoral Fellowship opportunity at the Faculty of Information, supervised by Christoph Becker, focused on post-growth computing, care, sufficiency, and alternative technological futures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JSD Lab Newsletter – Fall 2025</title><link href="/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JSD Lab Newsletter – Fall 2025" /><published>2025-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="welcome-to-the-first-edition-of-the-jsd-lab-newsletter-this-year-has-been-full-of-creative-experimentation-collaborative-research-and-new-local-and-international-partnerships-were-excited-to-share-highlights-from-our-community">Welcome to the first edition of the JSD Lab newsletter. This year has been full of creative experimentation, collaborative research, and new local and international partnerships. We’re excited to share highlights from our community.</h2>

<figure class="figure">
  <a class="figure-image" aria-label="figure link">
    <img src="/images/fall_2025.png" style="
        width: auto;
        max-height: unset;
      " alt="figure image" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />
  </a>
  
</figure>

<div align="center">
  Not all is work at the JSD. In 2025, we also gathered for picnics, hikes and games!<br />

</div>
<hr />

<h1>Contents</h1>

<p>
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#welcome-to-the-lab">WELCOME TO THE LAB!</a><br />
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#achievements-and-collaborations">ACHIEVEMENTS AND COLLABORATIONS</a><br />
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#projects">PROJECTS</a><br />
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#research-funding">RESEARCH FUNDING</a><br />
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#publications">PUBLICATIONS</a><br />
  <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/2025/12/16/jsd-newsletter-2025.html#coming-up">COMING UP</a>
</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="subscribe-to-the-jsd-lab-newsletter"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/-2dkjtFJsIalR1iNIqPSAUj+zGMXVu9I+AV2NerRQ2M/"><strong>Subscribe to the JSD Lab Newsletter</strong></a></h1>

<hr />

<h1 id="welcome-to-the-lab">Welcome to the Lab!</h1>
<h2 id="this-fall-the-jsd-lab-welcomed-four-graduate-students">This fall, the JSD Lab welcomed four graduate students.</h2>

<p><strong>Nadia Mariyan Smith</strong> is a PhD student in the Faculty of Information at the University of Toronto. With a background in community work, they are interested in justice-oriented, more-than-human design approaches that emphasize collective well-being and ecological sustainability. Nadia holds a Master of Information in User Experience Design and a Bachelor of Fine Arts in Photography.</p>

<p><strong>Nils Bonfils</strong> is a PhD student in the Faculty of Information at UofT. After completing his BSc and MSc degrees in Computer Science at EPFL, he worked in the banking and telecom industries as a Software Engineer for a few years. This allowed him to recognize the proportions and unsustainability of modern technological trends. He decided to pursue a PhD to explore and understand alternative ontologies in which information technology practices can be made more sustainable. His research interests span across Information, Computer Science, STS and the Environment. Other subtopics of interest are permacomputing, technology otherwise, convivial computing and digital degrowth.</p>

<p><strong>Rowan O.A. Munson</strong> is a PhD student at the Faculty of Information at the University of Toronto. His research interests focus on reconnecting technology to people, place, and planet. He is particularly interested in methods that are participatory, that broaden perspectives beyond WEIRD (Western, Educated, Industrialized, Rich, and Democratic) contexts, and that bridge academic theory and industry practice to create real-world impact. Previously, Rowan managed social research projects for UK Government agencies and charities, and published and lectured in Health and Social Care. He has advocated for policy changes to address social and environmental injustices and continues to engage in advocacy efforts to drive meaningful change. He holds an MSc in Behavioural and Data Science from the University of Warwick, UK; and a BA in Philosophy, Politics, and Economics from the University of Oxford, UK.</p>

<p><strong>Cristian Velasquez</strong> is an artist, photographer, and specialist in digital communication strategies and content production. He is currently pursuing a Master of Information at the University of Toronto, where he also leads communications and engagement for both the Just Sustainability Design Lab and the Knowledge Media Design Institute. Cristian’s artistic practice centers on documentation, making marginalized cultural practices and community histories visible. Over the past two years, he has been developing an ongoing visual archive of Toronto’s nightlife and culture. He has previously worked at the University of Toronto Scarborough Library, where he led initiatives to mobilize digital collections. In Colombia, he worked at the Ministry of Culture, contributing to the design and implementation of inclusion and diversity policies, advancing national literacy initiatives, and supporting public education and engagement.</p>

<h2 id="the-jsd-lab-is-happy-to-host-two-international-graduate-students-in-2025">The JSD Lab is happy to host two International Graduate students in 2025.</h2>

<p><strong>Victoria Landau</strong> investigates how cultural and research institutions approach digital sustainability, preservation, and curation. Her doctoral research at the University of Basel examines how institutional decision-making shapes heritage collections, both analog and digital, and how open standards support long-term access and preservation. We are grateful for the insight and energy she brought to our community. Wishing you continued success on your PhD journey, Victoria!</p>

<p><strong>Verena Müller</strong> is a PhD candidate at the Technical University of Munich whose work connects technology, law, and environmental sustainability. After completing her degree in Law, she joined the Professorship for Law, Innovation and Legal Design at TUM as a researcher and doctoral candidate. Her research spans the intersection of technology, society, and regulation. Her current project focuses on AI regulation and environmental sustainability, exploring innovative approaches to integrate law and AI practices to promote “Sustainability by Design.” Verena joins us for Fall 2025 and Winter 2026.</p>

<h1 id="achievements-and-collaborations">Achievements and Collaborations</h1>

<h2 id="near-data-and-far-data-for-urban-sustainability-how-do-community-advocates-envision-data-intermediaries-received-a-best-paper-award-at-acm-cscw-2025">“Near Data” and “Far Data” for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries?” received a Best Paper Award at ACM CSCW 2025.</h2>

<p>Authored by <strong>Han Qiao, Siyi Wu, and Christoph Becker</strong>, <a href="https://programs.sigchi.org/cscw/2025/program/content/211549">the winning paper</a> explores how community organizations navigate and negotiate data, ranging from local, lived information (“near data”) to large scale, processed datasets (“far data”). The study uncovers design possibilities for tools that center community expertise in building sustainable urban futures. PhD Candidate Han Qiao, who presented the work, grounds her doctoral research in a deceptively simple question: How do our everyday encounters with data influence the way we imagine—and shape—the cities around us? Her dissertation examines how our interactions with data inform our relationships to physical spaces and our collective imaginaries of urban futures.</p>

<p>This research continues through the <a href="https://schoolofcities.utoronto.ca/programs-opportunities/urban-challenge-grant/urban-challenge-grants-4">School of Cities Urban Challenge Grant (2025–2027)</a>, in collaboration with the Visionary Communities team in Scarborough. Together, we are developing practices that make heavily processed (far) data relevant for local knowledge contexts and aspirations, and re-embed community generated knowledges and aspirations (near data) in a far-data context to help municipal decision-makers better recognize, value, and act upon the insights and aspirations of community-based changemakers. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3710901">Read the full text.</a></p>

<h2 id="climate-change-what-is-computings-responsibility-reflections-from-the-dagstuhl-perspectives-workshop">Climate Change: What Is Computing’s Responsibility? Reflections from the Dagstuhl Perspectives Workshop</h2>

<p>In March 2025, a group of leading practitioners, policy experts, and researchers — including <strong>Christoph Becker</strong> — convened at Dagstuhl Leibniz Center for Informatics in Germany on invitation of the ACM to examine a pressing question: What is computing’s responsibility in the current climate crisis? The resulting <strong>Dagstuhl Manifesto</strong> is a wide-ranging call for a fundamental shift in how computational systems are designed, deployed, and governed.</p>

<p>The Manifesto challenges the assumption that efficiency gains or technological optimism alone can offset the rapidly escalating environmental impacts of digital infrastructures. Instead, it argues for reorienting computing toward sufficiency, long-term durability, human rights, and planetary boundaries. It underscores the need for transparent environmental assessments, a stronger role for computing professionals in shaping digital policy, and a renewed commitment to climate-conscious education and practice. For those working at the intersection of technology, sustainability, and justice, this document offers an essential framework for the years ahead. <a href="https://doi.org/10.4230/DagMan.11.1.1">Read the full text.</a></p>

<h2 id="resisting-genai-and-big-tech-in-higher-education">Resisting GenAI and Big Tech in Higher Education</h2>

<p>On November 25, an international panel of scholar-activists came together to examine the expanding influence of generative AI across universities and the urgent need to push back. From escalating energy and water consumption to disruptions in learning, academic integrity, and governance, the session unpacked the social, environmental, and political risks of AI’s rapid adoption.</p>

<p>Speakers included Christoph Becker (University of Toronto), Mary Finley-Brook (University of Richmond), Dan McQuillan (Goldsmiths, University of London), Sinéad Sheehan (University of Galway), Jennie Stephens (National University of Ireland Maynooth), and Paul Lachapelle (Montana State University). They shared concrete examples of resistance and refusal, offering pathways for collective action and for challenging the narrative that AI’s expansion is inevitable. If you missed the live event, you can now <a href="https://tubedu.org/w/teHCy6pkiKpS64j6F4CBgC?">watch the full recording here</a></p>

<h2 id="from-tech-lash-to-tech-fash-strategic-reflections-on-a-decade-of-collective-organizing-in-computing">From Tech Lash to Tech Fash: Strategic Reflections on a Decade of Collective Organizing in Computing</h2>

<p>On August 19, as part of the Aarhus 2025 conference, this workshop brought together seasoned and early-career technologists, practitioners, and scholar-activists to collectively reflect on how the field has shifted over the past decade from what Tamara Kneese has described as “techlash” to “tech fash” (Kneese, 2025). Participants explored how lessons from struggles around misinformation, algorithmic bias, surveillance capitalism, and tech worker organizing might inform contemporary resistance to the growing power of a techno-fascist oligarchy. By bridging past and present moments, the session created space for collective sense-making and strategic thinking about how to respond to today’s intersecting social, political, and technological crises.</p>

<p>Learn more about the discussions and reflections from the workshop:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Linda Huber, Pedro Reynolds-Cuéllar, Alicia DeVrio, Jensine Raihan, Cella M. Sum, Lynn Dombrowski, Justine Zhang, Christoph Becker, Lilly Irani, P. M. Krafft, and Margaret Hughes. 2025. From Tech Lash to Tech Fash: Strategic Reflections on a Decade of Collective Organizing in Computing. In Adjunct Proceedings of the Sixth Decennial Aarhus Conference: Computing X Crisis (AAR Adjunct ’25). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, Article 26, 1–4. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3737609.3747097">https://doi.org/10.1145/3737609.3747097</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="two-of-our-members-are-now-phd-candidates">Two of our members are now PhD Candidates!</h2>

<p><strong>Eshta Bhardwaj</strong> defended her thesis proposal titled <em>“Adopting a Data Curation Lens for Rigorous, Reflexive, and Responsible Machine Learning Data Practices.”</em> Her research focuses on the role of data practices within machine learning and how to augment ML dataset development processes with data curation principles, concerns of fairness, accountability, and transparency in “data work” within predictive modelling, and how to design interventions in data practices to aid in decision-making for environmental sustainability.</p>

<p><strong>Han Qiao</strong> defended her thesis proposal titled <em>“Designing with Data Near and Far: Making Information Visceral for Imagining and Navigating Sustainable Futures.”</em> Her ongoing work in human-computer interaction looks into how data and data tools shape our relationship with urban spaces and collective imagineries of urban futures. She hopes to continue exploring ways of supporting interaction with data through creative practices and understanding the effects of these alternative ways of visualizing data.</p>

<h1 id="projects">Projects</h1>

<h2 id="save-the-ai-holding-big-tech-accountable-through-creativity-and-humour">Save the AI: Holding Big Tech Accountable through Creativity and Humour</h2>

<p>This February, the JSD Lab launched Save the AI, a creative campaign that turns critical insights about AI’s environmental and social impacts into engaging public materials. Thanks to collaborators across the world, the campaign is now available in nine languages.</p>

<p>Save the AI uses humour as a bridge—connecting people’s basic needs such as clean water, electricity, and air to the resource-intensive infrastructures powering AI. By bridging the psychological distance between everyday life and far-off data centers, the project invites people to rethink the hidden footprints of today’s technological systems.</p>

<p>Our team presented this work at <a href="https://facctconference.org/">ACM FAccT 2025</a>, <a href="https://compass.acm.org/">COMPASS 2025</a> and <a href="https://kdd2025.kdd.org/">KDD 2025</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Han Qiao, Eshta Bhardwaj, Victoria G. D. Landau, Nils Bonfils, Monica Iqbal, Olya Jaworsky, Rowan O.A. Munson, Lena Rubisova, Nadia Mariyan Smith, Ayusha Thapa, and Christoph Becker. 2025. Are You Thirsty? So is Your AI.  Proc. of the 2025 ACM SIGCAS/SIGCHI Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS ‘25). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 811–816. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3736308">https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3736308</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Eshta Bhardwaj, Han Qiao, Rowan O.A. Munson, and Christoph Becker. 2025. Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability. Proc. of the 2025 ACM SIGCAS/SIGCHI Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS ‘25). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 831–836. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3737682">https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3737682</a></p>
</blockquote>

<div align="center">
  <strong>Follow Save the AI</strong><br />

</div>

<table style="border-collapse: collapse; margin: 0 auto;">
  <tr>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://savethe.ai">Website</a>
    </td>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://mastodon.social/@savetheAI">Mastodon</a>
    </td>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/savetheai.bsky.social">Bluesky</a>
    </td>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://www.instagram.com/savetheai">Instagram</a>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>

<h2 id="torontowarwick-collaboration-on-data-justice-social-justice-and-sustainability">Toronto–Warwick Collaboration on Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability</h2>

<p>The JSD Lab (University of Toronto) and the Centre for Interdisciplinary Methodologies (University of Warwick) have launched a new partnership to strengthen research and PhD training at the intersection of Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability. Funded through the 2025–2026 University of Toronto–University of Warwick Joint Seed Fund, the initiative is led by Dr. Siddharth De Souza and Professor Christoph Becker, and organized by PhD Student Rowan O.A. Munson.</p>

<p>Emerging data technologies often exacerbate social inequity and climate change, two of the most pressing challenges facing the world today, with their capacities to digitally monitor, sort, and control individuals and communities while consuming vast human and planetary resources in the process. The Universities of Toronto and Warwick are preparing our PhD students to take a leading role in addressing these global challenges by taking a global approach to PhD research and education that centers Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability in Technology Design.</p>

<p>The project is already underway, with three workshops hosted between November and December, 2025:</p>

<p><strong>“In which we shall question the supposed inevitability of artificial intelligence and what we might do about it.”</strong> With contributions from T.L. Cowan, Alessandro Delfanti, Noortje Marres and Sanjay Sharma.</p>

<p><strong>“Methodological Approaches to Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability.”</strong> Featuring Han Qiao, Kavin Narasimhan, Nadia Mariyan Smith and Nils Bonfils.</p>

<p><strong>“Academic as Activist: The role of the university in facilitating social change.”</strong> With contributions from Siddharth De Souza, Rafael Grohmann, Carlos Cámara-Menoyo, and Vera Khovanskaya.</p>

<h2 id="limits-2025-computing-within-planetary-boundaries">LIMITS 2025: Computing Within Planetary Boundaries</h2>

<p>JSD Lab Lead Christoph Becker co-chaired LIMITS 2025, a globally distributed, online-first conference focused on envisioning and enacting forms of computing that respect and operate within planetary boundaries. With over 200 participants joining from multiple continents, LIMITS continues to grow as the central venue for rethinking computing in a world of ecological and social constraints. This year LIMITS features two contributions from the JSD lab:</p>

<p><strong>An Empirical Inquiry into Surveillance Capitalism: Web Tracking</strong>
<strong>by Nils Bonfils at LIMITS 2025</strong></p>

<p>Nils Bonfils presented new empirical research on the mechanisms of Surveillance Capitalism as they unfold across the contemporary web. Drawing on longitudinal data from WhoTracks.Me (2017–2025) and publicly available SEC filings, the study maps the tracking practices of major tech companies—Google, Apple, Facebook, Amazon, and Microsoft. The analysis highlights Google’s pervasive presence across the web, proposes a three-tier hierarchy of GAFAM actors in the surveillance ecosystem, and identifies emerging forms of tracking designed to evade detection.
The work also reflects on the broader social and environmental costs of tracking-driven business models and points to alternative technologies, such as the Gemini protocol, that challenge extractive data practices. By grounding discussions of Surveillance Capitalism in empirical evidence, this contribution strengthens ongoing efforts to rethink digital infrastructures in more equitable and sustainable directions.<a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2508.07454">Read the full text here.</a></p>

<p><strong>Exploring the World3 Model to Assess Computing’s Impact on Planetary Boundaries</strong>
<strong>by Nara Guliyeva, Eshta Bhardwaj, and Christoph Becker</strong></p>

<p>Another contribution from the JSD Lab examined whether the updated World3-03 system dynamics model, a foundational tool first introduced in <a href="https://collections.dartmouth.edu/content/deliver/inline/meadows/pdf/meadows_ltg-001.pdf?_gl=1*tj06fo*_ga*..*_ga_X6T5RM37EZ*czE3NjQ1OTEyNzQkbzIkZzAkdDE3NjQ1OTEyODQkajUwJGw2025NDM0MDU1NDIuMTc2MTIzMTQ0NgwJGgw">Limits to Growth</a>, can be adapted to understand how today’s rapidly expanding computing infrastructures affect planetary boundaries.</p>

<p>With global data center development accelerating, particularly in support of AI systems, the authors asked whether World3-03 could meaningfully simulate the environmental consequences of resource-intensive computing. By integrating new AI-related variables, including data-center-driven pollution and growth trajectories, the team created an augmented scenario within the model. Their findings show that the model responds predictably to these additions, indicating that World3-03 is a viable quantitative tool for exploring how computing contributes to ecological strain. The paper outlines future research directions for using system dynamics to study the long-term environmental implications of AI and data infrastructure—supporting deeper, evidence-driven conversations about the sustainability of computing within planetary limits.<a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2510.07634">Read the full text here.</a></p>

<p>The LIMITS community brings together designers, engineers, artists, and scholars to explore questions around resource constraints, climate justice, transitional systems, and alternative imaginaries for technology design. Christoph Becker will also co-organize <a href="https://computingwithinlimits.org">LIMITS 2026</a></p>

<h1 id="research-funding">Research Funding</h1>

<p>Alongside the School of Cities Urban Challenge Grant supporting our project Centering Community in Data Ecosystems: Integrating Near Data and Far Data for Just Sustainable Neighborhoods, and the Toronto–Warwick Joint Seed Fund for Developing Collaboration in Research and Education, the JSD Lab was also pleased to receive funding from NSERC and SSHRC:</p>

<p><strong>NSERC Discovery Grant (2025–2030)</strong> Evidence-based sustainability assessments for ecologically responsible decision-making in software engineering</p>

<p><strong>SSHRC Insight Development Grant (2025–2027)</strong> Text Mining Higher Education Discourse for New Insights on Sustainability: A Pilot Study. <strong>Co-PI: Elizabeth Buckner, Ontario Institute for Studies in Education</strong></p>

<h1 id="publications">Publications</h1>

<p>Explore recent publications from the JSD Lab members and collaborators:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Priyanka Verma, Christoph Becker, and Samar Sabie. 2025. <strong>17 Years of Fintech for Financial Inclusion: A Systematic Review and Critical Value Analysis</strong>. Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 9, 7, Article CSCW358 (November 2025), 33 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3757539">https://doi.org/10.1145/3757539</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Vishal Sharma, Asra Sakeen Wani, Raphaël Marée, Christoph Becker, Douglas Schuler, Aparajita Marathe, Neha Kumar, Han Qiao, Rikke Hagensby Jensen, and Anupriya Tuli. 2025. <strong>Challenging the Growth Narrative in and Through HCI</strong>. XRDS 31, 4 (Summer 2025), 12–18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3744691">https://doi.org/10.1145/3744691</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Han Qiao, Eshta Bhardwaj, Victoria G. D. Landau, Nils Bonfils, Monica Iqbal, Olya Jaworsky, Rowan O.A. Munson, Lena Rubisova, Nadia Mariyan Smith, Ayusha Thapa, and Christoph Becker. 2025. <strong>Are You Thirsty? So is Your AI</strong>.  Proc. of the 2025 ACM SIGCAS/SIGCHI Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS ‘25). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 811–816. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3736308">https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3736308</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Eshta Bhardwaj, Han Qiao, Rowan O.A. Munson, and Christoph Becker. 2025. <strong>Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability</strong>.  Proc. of the 2025 ACM SIGCAS/SIGCHI Conference on Computing and Sustainable Societies (COMPASS ‘25). Association for Computing Machinery, New York, NY, USA, 831–836. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3737682">https://doi.org/10.1145/3715335.3737682</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Han Qiao, Siyi Wu, and Christoph Becker. 2025. <strong>“Near Data” and “Far Data” for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries?</strong> Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 9, 2, Article CSCW003 (May 2025), 30 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3710901">https://doi.org/10.1145/3710901</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nils Bonfils, 2025. <strong>An Empirical Inquiry into Surveillance Capitalism: Web Tracking</strong>. Post-proc. paper presented at LIMITS 2025: 11th Workshop on Computing within Limits. (June 2025), 10 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2508.07454">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2508.07454</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nara Guliyeva, Eshta Bhardwaj, Christoph Becker, 2025. <strong>Exploring the Viability of the Updated World3 Model for Examining the Impact of Computing on Planetary Boundaries</strong> Post-proc. paper presented at LIMITS 2025: 11th Workshop on Computing within Limits. (June 2025), 25 pages <a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2510.07634">https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2510.07634</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bran Knowles, Vicki L. Hanson, Christoph Becker, Mike Berners-Lee, Andrew A. Chien, Benoit Combemale, Vlad Coroamă, Koen De Bosschere, Yi Ding, Adrian Friday, Boris Gamazaychikov, Lynda Hardman, Simon Hinterholzer, Mattias Höjer, Lynn Kaack, Lenneke Kuijer, Anne-Laure Ligozat, Jan Tobias Muehlberg, Yunmook Nah, Thomas Olsson, Anne-Cécile Orgerie, Daniel Pargman, Birgit Penzenstadler, Tom Romanoff, Emma Strubell, Colin Venters, and Junhua Zhao, 2025. <strong>Climate Change: What is Computing’s Responsibility? (Dagstuhl Perspectives Workshop 25122)</strong>. In Dagstuhl Manifestos, Volume 11, Issue 1, pp. 1-18, Schloss Dagstuhl – Leibniz-Zentrum für Informatik (2025) <a href="https://doi.org/10.4230/DagMan.11.1.1">https://doi.org/10.4230/DagMan.11.1.1</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Harshit Gujral, Om Damani, Anshul Agarwal, Christoph Becker, Meredith Franklin, Teresa Kramarz, Ronak Sutaria, Sagnik Dey, Steve Easterbrook, 2025. <strong>Reimagining urban air-quality governance: A systems-thinking framework</strong>. The Science of the Total Environment, 1010, 181059. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.181059">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2025.181059</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="coming-up">Coming up</h1>
<h2 id="jsd-lab-at-chi-2026-the-worlds-leading-hci-conference">JSD Lab at CHI 2026, the World’s Leading HCI Conference</h2>

<p>We’re delighted to share that the JSD Lab will have two contributions at the ACM CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2026), the premier international venue for Human–Computer Interaction research. CHI 2026 will take place in Barcelona at the Centre de Convencions Internacional de Barcelona.</p>

<p><strong>Crip HCI: Cyborg Perspectives on Disability Justice</strong>
Professor Christoph Becker brings together a collective of disabled researchers and artists in organizing Crip HCI: Cyborg Perspectives on Disability Justice. This workshop brings together medical “cyborgs”—individuals living with devices such as insulin pumps, prosthetics, pacemakers, and sensors—to reflect on the politics, vulnerabilities, and creativity embedded in cyborg life. Grounded in disability justice, crip theory, and lived experience, the workshop challenges extractive, techno-solutionist approaches and centers the knowledge of disabled people as foundational to imagining new sociotechnical futures. Participants will share work, build community, and explore how cyborg perspectives can reshape research, design, and policy in HCI. <a href="https://t1dsign.org/chi-2026">More info here</a></p>

<p><strong>Cultivating Pedagogies for Post-Growth HCI</strong></p>

<p>A cross-institutional team including the JSD Lab researcher Han Qiao and Professor Christoph Becker will co-organize Cultivating Pedagogies for Post-Growth HCI, a workshop that asks how HCI education can move beyond “bigger-and-faster” mindsets toward practices grounded in sufficiency, repair, and care.</p>

<p>Drawing on the growing field of post-growth HCI, the workshop invites educators, students, and practitioners to co-design a “living syllabus,” rethink evaluation systems, and explore how teaching itself can serve as an infrastructural practice for sustainable and just futures in computing.</p>

<p>This contribution continues the momentum from previous CHI workshops and strengthens an international community dedicated to post-growth teaching and practice. More info soon</p>

<hr />

<h1 id="subscribe-to-the-jsd-lab-newsletter-1"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/-2dkjtFJsIalR1iNIqPSAUj+zGMXVu9I+AV2NerRQ2M/"><strong>Subscribe to the JSD Lab Newsletter</strong></a></h1>

<hr />

<h1 id="the-just-sustainability-design-lab-online">The Just Sustainability Design Lab Online</h1>

<table style="border-collapse: collapse; margin: 0 auto;">
  <tr>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/">The JSD Lab Website</a>
    </td>
    <td style="border:none; padding: 0.5rem 1rem;">
      <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/just-sustainability-design-lab">LinkedIn</a>
    </td>
  </tr>
</table>]]></content><author><name>cristian-velasquez</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to the first edition of the JSD Lab newsletter. This year has been full of creative experimentation, collaborative research, and new local and international partnerships. We’re excited to share highlights from our community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Near Data and Far Data - Best Paper Award at CSCW 2025</title><link href="/2025/12/13/CSCW-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Near Data and Far Data - Best Paper Award at CSCW 2025" /><published>2025-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/12/13/CSCW-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/12/13/CSCW-award.html"><![CDATA[<p>JSD Lab members Han Qiao, Siyi Wu, and Christoph Becker received the Best Paper Award at the 28th ACM SIGCHI Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work &amp; Social Computing (CSCW 2025) in Bergen, Norway. In this blog post, we share some key insights from the paper and we invite you to read more about the paper here:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Han Qiao, Siyi Wu, and Christoph Becker. 2025. “Near Data” and “Far Data” for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries? Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 9, 2, Article CSCW003 (May 2025), 30 pages. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3710901">https://doi.org/10.1145/3710901</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Near Data” and “Far Data” for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries?, examines how advocates use data in their work and how they envision data intermediaries tools for pursuing more sustainable urban futures. Based on interviews with 17 advocates from 23 community groups, the study introduces the concepts of “near data” and “far data,” identifying pathways for data intermediaries to align data exploration with storytelling, communicate context and uncertainty, and decenter artifacts for relationship-building.
The quality of “near” and “far” describes how one relates to the data that they work with. This relationship is fluid, dynamic and relational. Near data and far data identifies two extremes on a spectrum of near and far. When one views, makes sense of, or works with data, the distance between the person and the dataset can sit anywhere on the spectrum. Thus this is not a binary categorical distinction. A dataset that is close to someone, might also appear to be far to others. For example, someone living in a neighborhood will likely have a very different relationship to that neighborhood’s active living score than someone encountering the same data from elsewhere. Similarly, a person living with diabetes may feel far closer to data generated by their glucose-monitoring device than someone without that lived experience. When data feels “near,” it is often accompanied by stronger emotional and visceral connections, and can afford a greater sense of agency to act. However, far data can also be valuable and necessary in many situations. Data that is abstracted, aggregated, or distanced can protect privacy, could reduce harm, and support the emotional labour of frontline workers.</p>

<p>We are currently working to further articulate this concept by examining what aspects of data shape how people relate to it. We also explore how reflecting on these relationships can make visible the politics and power embedded in data work, open up new design spaces, and support data practices grounded in data justice and data feminism. We hope to contribute to ongoing efforts to reimagine and pursue urban futures that are more just, sustainable and inclusive.</p>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Near Data” and “Far Data” for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries?” received a Best Paper Award at ACM CSCW 2025.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Resisting GenAI and Big Tech in Higher Education</title><link href="/2025/12/12/resisting-ai-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resisting GenAI and Big Tech in Higher Education" /><published>2025-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/12/12/resisting-ai-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/12/12/resisting-ai-education.html"><![CDATA[<p>On November 25, an international panel of scholar-activists came together to examine the expanding influence of generative AI across universities and the urgent need to push back. From escalating energy and water consumption to disruptions in learning, academic integrity, and governance, the session unpacked the social, environmental, and political risks of AI’s rapid adoption.</p>

<p>Speakers included Christoph Becker (University of Toronto), Mary Finley-Brook (University of Richmond), Dan McQuillan (Goldsmiths, University of London), Sinéad Sheehan (University of Galway), Jennie Stephens (National University of Ireland Maynooth), and Paul Lachapelle (Montana State University). They shared concrete examples of resistance and refusal, offering pathways for collective action and for challenging the narrative that AI’s expansion is inevitable.</p>

<p>Co-sponsored by:</p>

<p><a href="https://climatejusticeuniversitiesunion.org/">Climate Justice Universities Union</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.campusclimatenetwork.org/">Climate Campus Network</a></p>

<h1 id="resources">Resources</h1>

<h2 id="if-you-missed-the-live-event-you-can-now-watch-the-full-recording-here">If you missed the live event, you can now <a href="https://tubedu.org/w/teHCy6pkiKpS64j6F4CBgC?">watch the full recording here</a></h2>

<h2 id="more-information-available-in-this-resource-document-with-links-to-recent-news-articles-movements-and-organizations">More information available in this <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/resistinggenerativeai/LinksResources.pdf">resource document</a> with links to recent news, articles, movements, and organizations.</h2>]]></content><author><name>cristian-velasquez</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Generative AI is permeating higher education in many different ways—it is all around us and increasingly embedded in university work and life, even if we don’t want to use it. What can we do? How do we resist?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building research and PhD collaborations on Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability</title><link href="/2025/07/18/toronto-warwick-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building research and PhD collaborations on Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability" /><published>2025-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/07/18/toronto-warwick-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/07/18/toronto-warwick-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p>Emerging data technologies often exacerbate social inequity and climate change, two of the most pressing challenges facing the world today, with their capacities to digitally monitor, sort, and control individuals and communities while consuming vast human and planetary resources in the process. The Universities of Toronto and Warwick are preparing our PhD students to take a leading role in addressing these global challenges by taking a global approach to PhD research and education that centers Data Justice, Social Justice, and Sustainability in Technology Design.</p>

<p>Warwick PI: <a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/cross_fac/cim/people/siddharth-de-souza/">Dr Siddharth De Souza</a></p>

<p>U of T PI: <a href="https://discover.research.utoronto.ca/21004-christoph-becker">Professor Christoph Becker</a></p>

<p>Funded 2025-2026 by the <a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/global/theamericas/torontowarwickjointseedfund/">University of Toronto and University of Warwick Joint Seed Fund</a></p>]]></content><author><name>rowan-munson</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We're collaborating with the University of Warwick to address the global challenges of social inequity and climate change.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COMPASS Arts &amp;amp; Demos: Are you Thirsty? So is your AI.</title><link href="/2025/07/14/compass-artdemo-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COMPASS Arts &amp;amp; Demos: Are you Thirsty? So is your AI." /><published>2025-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/07/14/compass-artdemo-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/07/14/compass-artdemo-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>COMPASS Arts &amp; Demos: Are you Thirsty? So is your AI.</strong><br />
<strong>July 24 from 9:00am-6:00pm at Bahen Centre for Information Technology 2nd Floor</strong></p>

<p>The JSD lab will have an art and demo installation at the COMPASS conference on July 24 showcasing artifacts from <a href="Savethe.AI">Savethe.AI</a>. Our installation will be at the Bahen Centre for Information Technology on the 2nd Floor from 9am-5pm, with the Arts &amp; Demos reception from 5-6pm.</p>

<p><strong>Come say hi to the organizers!</strong></p>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/han-qiao.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Han Qiao">
    <img src="/images/han.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Han Qiao
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/eshta-bhardwaj.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Eshta Bhardwaj">
    <img src="/images/Eshta.png" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Eshta Bhardwaj
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Candidate, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/rowan-munson.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Rowan O.A. Munson">
    <img src="/images/RowanMunson.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Rowan O.A. Munson
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/nils-bonfils.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Nils Bonfils">
    <img src="/images/Nils.jpeg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Nils Bonfils
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/nadia-smith.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Nadia Mariyan Smith">
    <img src="/images/Nadia.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Nadia Mariyan Smith
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/victoria-landau.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Victoria G. D. Landau">
    <img src="/images/Victoria.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Victoria G. D. Landau
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-magnifying-glass"></i>
            <span>Visiting PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/christoph-becker.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Christoph Becker">
    <img src="/images/Christoph%20Becker_copyright.png" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Christoph Becker
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-microscope"></i>
            <span>Professor, Faculty of Information and School of the Environment</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Come check out our art installation at the COMPASS conference, please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FAccT CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI</title><link href="/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAccT CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI" /><published>2025-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>FAccT’25 CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI</strong><br />
<strong>June 23 from 1030am-1230pm ET, Virtual</strong></p>

<p><strong>Session Description:</strong>
Our interactive CRAFT workshop session uses satire and creative expression to 
facilitate and strengthen collective organizing around the environmental damages caused by AI systems.</p>

<p>The JSD lab has developed a distributed satirical campaign to <a href="https://savethe.ai/">Savethe.AI</a> which uses humour 
to connect individuals’ and communities’ needs for Earth’s resources with the evidence 
of just how much of these resources are now being claimed for the data centres running generative AI. 
By connecting our thirst with a data center’s cooling system, the campaign addresses psychological 
distance: it is very hard to relate personally to the distant data centers where generative AI models do their work.</p>

<p>In our CRAFT workshop session, we will build on the satirical angle and facilitate 
a creative humorous engagement with questions of individual agency, community experiences, and 
collective resistance. We collectively explore ecological and social impacts of data centers 
and platforms that are already felt by diverse communities. These impacts vary greatly in place and 
time and are documented primarily by the tireless work of organizers, civil society, and academics, 
while being obfuscated by the companies creating the situation.</p>

<p>Our workshop invites participants to collectively develop their own humorous ideas and materials 
that express the absurdity of those harms being taken for granted and denied.</p>

<p>Through this creative process, 
we hope to achieve both a collective learning process, 
foster a sense of collective agency, possibly develop visual 
materials that the community can use, and contribute to community 
building in the face of the issues of accountability, transparency, and 
ecological and social harms that result from rampant AI.</p>

<p>Please note that in order to attend, all participants must register for ACM FAccT. <a href="https://facctconference.org/2025/registration">https://facctconference.org/2025/registration</a>. 
More details about our CRAFT session can be found <a href="https://programs.sigchi.org/facct/2025/my-schedule/content/198133">here</a> on the 
FAccT schedule which also includes the Zoom event link.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The JSD lab is hosting an online FAccT CRAFT session about the environmental impacts of AI. Please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability</title><link href="/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability" /><published>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability</strong><br />
<strong>July 22 from 2:00-6:00pm at MY330 (Myhal Centre) and Online (Zoom)</strong></p>

<p><strong>Call for Participation:</strong>
Join us for an interactive workshop that delves into the ecological and social impacts of data centers, the backbone of AI infrastructure. 
As AI scales up, so does the need for data centers, which has significant environmental and social repercussions often obscured by Big Tech. This workshop aims to 
illuminate these impacts and foster collective organizing around the harms caused by data centers.</p>

<p>In the first half, we will explore the local and global implications of data centers, encouraging participants to get to know the 
impacts of particular data centers in place. We will present key findings on the environmental degradation and social injustices linked to data center operations, 
highlighting the voices of grassroots organizers who have documented these harms.</p>

<p>The second half of the workshop will embrace creativity as a tool for resistance. We will work together, using humour, satire, and art to convey the 
increasing social and environmental resource consumption taking place in data centers. Together, we will brainstorm and develop visual materials that convey these messages, transforming despair into collective agency.</p>

<p>We invite activists, researchers, and community members to contribute their perspectives and creativity. By participating, you will help build a network of 
resistance against the negative impacts of data center infrastructure, fostering a sense of community and shared purpose.</p>

<p>Please register here to attend the workshop: <a href="https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/EEYh7mnHE+oT97BSUUNCvVR+H5d4ft2h3gkOkcRmveM/">https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/EEYh7mnHE+oT97BSUUNCvVR+H5d4ft2h3gkOkcRmveM/</a>. Please contact <a href="mailto:eshta.bhardwaj@mail.utoronto.ca">Eshta Bhardwaj</a> for any questions.</p>

<p><strong>Agenda:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>200 - 220: Workshop Introduction</li>
  <li>220 - 300: Guest Speaker Hanna Barakat’s talk on her recent <a href="https://www.themaybe.org/research/data-center-report-where-cloud-meets-cement">Case Study Analysis of Data Center Development</a></li>
  <li>300 - 330: Break</li>
  <li>330 - 400: Organizer Han Qiao speaks about workshop themes: art, humour, satire, absurdity, viscerality</li>
  <li>400 - 430: Attendees participate in an activity</li>
  <li>430 - 530: Reflections</li>
  <li>530 - 545: Workshop Conclusion</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Guest Speaker:</strong></p>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/hanna-barakat.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Hanna Barakat">
    <img src="/images/hanna_barakat.png" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Hanna Barakat
          </span>
        

        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<p><strong>Organizers:</strong></p>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/eshta-bhardwaj.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Eshta Bhardwaj">
    <img src="/images/Eshta.png" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Eshta Bhardwaj
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Candidate, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/han-qiao.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Han Qiao">
    <img src="/images/han.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Han Qiao
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/rowan-munson.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Rowan O.A. Munson">
    <img src="/images/RowanMunson.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Rowan O.A. Munson
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/nils-bonfils.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Nils Bonfils">
    <img src="/images/Nils.jpeg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Nils Bonfils
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/nadia-smith.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Nadia Mariyan Smith">
    <img src="/images/Nadia.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Nadia Mariyan Smith
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-graduation-cap"></i>
            <span>PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/victoria-landau.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Victoria G. D. Landau">
    <img src="/images/Victoria.jpg" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Victoria G. D. Landau
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-magnifying-glass"></i>
            <span>Visiting PhD Student, Faculty of Information</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>

<div class="portrait-wrapper">
  <a href="/members/christoph-becker.html" class="portrait" data-style="small" aria-label="Christoph Becker">
    <img src="/images/Christoph%20Becker_copyright.png" class="portrait-image" alt="member portrait" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />

    
      <span class="portrait-text">
        
          <span class="portrait-name">
            Christoph Becker
          </span>
        

        
          <span class="portrait-role">
            
            <i class="icon fa-solid fa-microscope"></i>
            <span>Professor, Faculty of Information and School of the Environment</span>
          </span>
        
      </span>
    
  </a>
</div>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for an interactive workshop that delves into the ecological and social impacts of data centers, please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JSD Lab at CHI 2025</title><link href="/2025/04/22/CHI2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JSD Lab at CHI 2025" /><published>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/04/22/CHI2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/04/22/CHI2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The JSD lab at CHI 2025</strong>\</p>

<p>JSD lab memebers will be participating at <a href="https://chi2025.acm.org/">CHI 2025</a>, taking place in Yokohama, Japan from April 26 to May 1. The conference brings together researchers, practitioners and industry leaders to showcase some of the latest research in human-computer interaction. Christoph Becker will be co-organizing a workshop on <a href="https://pointed-waterlily-f95.notion.site/Advancing-Post-growth-HCI-15dec6ab184b809b8692ec6a3d578089">Advancing Post-growth HCI</a>. Han Qiao will be presenting her paper written during her internship at Autodesk Research, titled “To Use or Not to Use: Impatience and Overreliance When Using Generative AI Productivity Support Tools.”</p>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Members of the JSD lab will be organizing a workshop and presenting at the ACM CHI conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research Collaboration Opportunity: Data Curation in Machine Learning</title><link href="/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Collaboration Opportunity: Data Curation in Machine Learning" /><published>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment.html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you interested in your data curation practices?</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> We are looking to collaborate with a ML group (industry or academia) who wants to review and 
refine their data practices for improved documentation and reflexivity of their ML data workflow and better ML model outcomes. 
Depending on what you are interested in, this collaboration could take different shapes: jointly evaluating datasets, organizing workshops, 
action research, or other activities. We provide more information and outline some options below.</p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> ML research has established that bias in models often causes 
discriminatory or unethical judgements towards specific populations. These biases are widely 
attributed to the choices made about datasets used for training ML models. Datasets are often reused across tasks 
which are outside the original context they were created for and appropriate data use is also hindered by the hidden, 
tacit, and undervalued nature of data work. The adoption of principles from archival studies and digital curation into 
dataset development processes for machine learning research has been found as one way to address these concerns. <strong>Data curation</strong> is a 
mature field with origins in librarianship and archives whose scholarship and thinking on data issues go back many centuries. It has 
found new relevance today as the field of machine learning is recognizing the importance of data curation to the advancement of both 
applications and fundamental understanding of machine learning models. In practice, it has been difficult to adopt these concepts 
because they do not easily apply.</p>

<p><strong>Background:</strong> This project will build on our previous work in applying data curation principles in ML dataset development. We 
have previously established how data curation principles can be applied to curate datasets in ML in practice. We translated 
data curation principles and concepts for the ML dataset development context and developed an evaluation framework (composed of a 
toolkit and rubric) for dataset documentation in ML. We presented first findings and a sample set of evaluations of ML datasets in a 
FAccT2024 paper (see <a href="https://youtu.be/C5VwJBE31JY?si=lFynqavsAiL8tPpF">talk</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3630106.3658955">paper</a>). We then examined how well data curation is currently performed in ML through a larger evaluation 
of NeurIPS datasets (accepted in the NeurIPS D&amp;B track in 2024, see <a href="https://youtu.be/uLsfFjbERAI">talk</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22473">paper</a>). Our 
findings lead to suggestions on where data curation in ML can be improved.</p>

<p><strong>Research Opportunities:</strong> We are currently looking to collaborate with ML groups (industry or academia) who want to 
improve their data pipeline and practices and would be open to exploring how our framework can be adopted 
into their workflows. <strong>Our goal is to help improve data practices by applying data curation concepts; this collaborative study can have several formats and designs, we list a few versions below but are open to others based on the group’s needs and interests.</strong></p>

<p><u>Description:</u> We are looking to pilot our data curation for ML framework and integrate it into ML pipelines. This study aims 
to understand a ML group’s curation needs and collaboratively reflect on and enhance their data curation practices using 
our data curation framework. We anticipate that the collaborative process will result in a progressive learning cycle and this 
may lead to the framework evolving to better suit the needs of the ML group.</p>

<p><u>Requirements:</u></p>
<ul>
  <li>You are interested in improving your data practices. This is broadly 
construed - it includes data collection, data management, data processing and cleaning, data storage and overall data design decisions.</li>
  <li>You intend for the data to be used in a ML model. However, the approach does not have to be decided (and the curation process can also help guide this decision).</li>
  <li>Your work can be at <strong>any stage of the data pipeline</strong> - whether it be data collection or data management. For example, if the group is looking to start data collection or is ready to use the dataset within a model, we can make recommendations on how curation principles can be applied to better document and steward the data.</li>
  <li>The dataset(s) can be of <strong>any modality</strong> and regarding <strong>any domain</strong>.</li>
  <li>The dataset(s) can be <strong>new or already existing</strong>. For example, if the 
ML group often uses existing datasets, we can evaluate datasets using the framework to inform their selection of which datasets to reuse.</li>
</ul>

<p><u>Expected Activities and Outcomes:</u> 
The findings from this study would result in <strong>1) improved joint understanding of the benefits resulting from data curation, 2) tailored insights for the team’s curation processes, and 3) deepened cross-disciplinary scholarship</strong>. The project 
would thus provide insights on practical approaches in performing and adopting data curation practices that result in improved datasets and consequently models.</p>

<p>Potential activities with the expected outcomes are listed below, this is not a comprehensive list and the activities will depend on the collaborative needs of the project.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Workshop to introduce data curation concepts</li>
  <li>Collaborative examination of current curation practices and proposal for improvements for data workflows</li>
  <li>Sample evaluations of dataset documentation for new datasets created by the ML team</li>
  <li>Sample evaluations of dataset documentation for existing datasets used by the ML team (or in consideration to be used)</li>
  <li>Examination of dataset(s) to glean usage to be applied for various ML efforts</li>
</ol>

<p>If you are interested, please contact Prof. Christoph Becker at <a href="mailto:christoph.becker@utoronto.ca">christoph.becker@utoronto.ca</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are looking to collaborate with a ML group (industry or academia) who wants to review and refine their data practices for improved documentation. Please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry></feed>