<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-20T15:17:55+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Just Sustainability Design</title><entry><title type="html">FAccT CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI</title><link href="/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAccT CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI" /><published>2025-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/06/05/craft-workshop-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>FAccT’25 CRAFT: Leveraging humour, satire, and art to engage with the environmental impacts of AI</strong>
<strong>June 23 from 1030am-1230pm ET, Virtual</strong></p>

<p><strong>Session Description:</strong>
Our interactive CRAFT workshop session uses satire and creative expression to 
facilitate and strengthen collective organizing around the environmental damages caused by AI systems.</p>

<p>The JSD lab has developed a distributed satirical campaign to <a href="https://savethe.ai/">Savethe.AI</a> which uses humour 
to connect individuals’ and communities’ needs for Earth’s resources with the evidence 
of just how much of these resources are now being claimed for the data centres running generative AI. 
By connecting our thirst with a data center’s cooling system, the campaign addresses psychological 
distance: it is very hard to relate personally to the distant data centers where generative AI models do their work.</p>

<p>In our CRAFT workshop session, we will build on the satirical angle and facilitate 
a creative humorous engagement with questions of individual agency, community experiences, and 
collective resistance. We collectively explore ecological and social impacts of data centers 
and platforms that are already felt by diverse communities. These impacts vary greatly in place and 
time and are documented primarily by the tireless work of organizers, civil society, and academics, 
while being obfuscated by the companies creating the situation.</p>

<p>Our workshop invites participants to collectively develop their own humorous ideas and materials 
that express the absurdity of those harms being taken for granted and denied.</p>

<p>Through this creative process, 
we hope to achieve both a collective learning process, 
foster a sense of collective agency, possibly develop visual 
materials that the community can use, and contribute to community 
building in the face of the issues of accountability, transparency, and 
ecological and social harms that result from rampant AI.</p>

<p>Please note that in order to attend, all participants must register for ACM FAccT. <a href="https://facctconference.org/2025/registration">https://facctconference.org/2025/registration</a>. 
More details about our CRAFT session can be found <a href="https://programs.sigchi.org/facct/2025/my-schedule/content/198133">here</a> on the 
FAccT schedule which also includes the Zoom event link.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The JSD lab is hosting an online FAccT CRAFT session about the environmental impacts of AI. Please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability</title><link href="/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability" /><published>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/05/29/compass-workshop-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>COMPASS Workshop: Humour as Resistance: Creative Approaches to Data Center Accountability</strong><br />
<strong>July 22 from 2:00-6:00pm at MY330 (Myhal Centre)</strong></p>

<p><strong>Call for Participation:</strong>
Join us for an interactive workshop that delves into the ecological and social impacts of data centers, the backbone of AI infrastructure. 
As AI scales up, so does the need for data centers, which has significant environmental and social repercussions often obscured by Big Tech. This workshop aims to 
illuminate these impacts and foster collective organizing around the harms caused by data centers.</p>

<p>In the first half, we will explore the local and global implications of data centers, encouraging participants to get to know the 
impacts of particular data centers in place. We will present key findings on the environmental degradation and social injustices linked to data center operations, 
highlighting the voices of grassroots organizers who have documented these harms.</p>

<p>The second half of the workshop will embrace creativity as a tool for resistance. We will work together, using humour, satire, and art to convey the 
increasing social and environmental resource consumption taking place in data centers. Together, we will brainstorm and develop visual materials that convey these messages, transforming despair into collective agency.</p>

<p>We invite activists, researchers, and community members to contribute their perspectives and creativity. By participating, you will help build a network of 
resistance against the negative impacts of data center infrastructure, fostering a sense of community and shared purpose.</p>

<p>Please register here to attend the workshop: <a href="https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/EEYh7mnHE+oT97BSUUNCvVR+H5d4ft2h3gkOkcRmveM/">https://cryptpad.fr/form/#/2/form/view/EEYh7mnHE+oT97BSUUNCvVR+H5d4ft2h3gkOkcRmveM/</a>. Please contact <a href="mailto:eshta.bhardwaj@mail.utoronto.ca">Eshta Bhardwaj</a> for any questions. 
Please note that in order to attend, all participants must register for ACM COMPASS. <a href="https://compass.acm.org/">https://compass.acm.org/</a></p>

<p><strong>Agenda:</strong>
<em>Coming soon!</em></p>

<p><strong>Speakers and Organizers:</strong>
<em>Coming soon!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for an interactive workshop that delves into the ecological and social impacts of data centers, please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">JSD Lab at CHI 2025</title><link href="/2025/04/22/CHI2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JSD Lab at CHI 2025" /><published>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/04/22/CHI2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/04/22/CHI2025.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The JSD lab at CHI 2025</strong>\</p>

<p>JSD lab memebers will be participating at <a href="https://chi2025.acm.org/">CHI 2025</a>, taking place in Yokohama, Japan from April 26 to May 1. The conference brings together researchers, practitioners and industry leaders to showcase some of the latest research in human-computer interaction. Christoph Becker will be co-organizing a workshop on <a href="https://pointed-waterlily-f95.notion.site/Advancing-Post-growth-HCI-15dec6ab184b809b8692ec6a3d578089">Advancing Post-growth HCI</a>. Han Qiao will be presenting her paper written during her internship at Autodesk Research, titled “To Use or Not to Use: Impatience and Overreliance When Using Generative AI Productivity Support Tools.”</p>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Members of the JSD lab will be organizing a workshop and presenting at the ACM CHI conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research Collaboration Opportunity: Data Curation in Machine Learning</title><link href="/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Collaboration Opportunity: Data Curation in Machine Learning" /><published>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/03/27/dcml_project_recruitment.html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you interested in your data curation practices?</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> We are looking to collaborate with a ML group (industry or academia) who wants to review and 
refine their data practices for improved documentation and reflexivity of their ML data workflow and better ML model outcomes. 
Depending on what you are interested in, this collaboration could take different shapes: jointly evaluating datasets, organizing workshops, 
action research, or other activities. We provide more information and outline some options below.</p>

<p><strong>Context:</strong> ML research has established that bias in models often causes 
discriminatory or unethical judgements towards specific populations. These biases are widely 
attributed to the choices made about datasets used for training ML models. Datasets are often reused across tasks 
which are outside the original context they were created for and appropriate data use is also hindered by the hidden, 
tacit, and undervalued nature of data work. The adoption of principles from archival studies and digital curation into 
dataset development processes for machine learning research has been found as one way to address these concerns. <strong>Data curation</strong> is a 
mature field with origins in librarianship and archives whose scholarship and thinking on data issues go back many centuries. It has 
found new relevance today as the field of machine learning is recognizing the importance of data curation to the advancement of both 
applications and fundamental understanding of machine learning models. In practice, it has been difficult to adopt these concepts 
because they do not easily apply.</p>

<p><strong>Background:</strong> This project will build on our previous work in applying data curation principles in ML dataset development. We 
have previously established how data curation principles can be applied to curate datasets in ML in practice. We translated 
data curation principles and concepts for the ML dataset development context and developed an evaluation framework (composed of a 
toolkit and rubric) for dataset documentation in ML. We presented first findings and a sample set of evaluations of ML datasets in a 
FAccT2024 paper (see <a href="https://youtu.be/C5VwJBE31JY?si=lFynqavsAiL8tPpF">talk</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3630106.3658955">paper</a>). We then examined how well data curation is currently performed in ML through a larger evaluation 
of NeurIPS datasets (accepted in the NeurIPS D&amp;B track in 2024, see <a href="https://youtu.be/uLsfFjbERAI">talk</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22473">paper</a>). Our 
findings lead to suggestions on where data curation in ML can be improved.</p>

<p><strong>Research Opportunities:</strong> We are currently looking to collaborate with ML groups (industry or academia) who want to 
improve their data pipeline and practices and would be open to exploring how our framework can be adopted 
into their workflows. <strong>Our goal is to help improve data practices by applying data curation concepts; this collaborative study can have several formats and designs, we list a few versions below but are open to others based on the group’s needs and interests.</strong></p>

<p><u>Description:</u> We are looking to pilot our data curation for ML framework and integrate it into ML pipelines. This study aims 
to understand a ML group’s curation needs and collaboratively reflect on and enhance their data curation practices using 
our data curation framework. We anticipate that the collaborative process will result in a progressive learning cycle and this 
may lead to the framework evolving to better suit the needs of the ML group.</p>

<p><u>Requirements:</u></p>
<ul>
  <li>You are interested in improving your data practices. This is broadly 
construed - it includes data collection, data management, data processing and cleaning, data storage and overall data design decisions.</li>
  <li>You intend for the data to be used in a ML model. However, the approach does not have to be decided (and the curation process can also help guide this decision).</li>
  <li>Your work can be at <strong>any stage of the data pipeline</strong> - whether it be data collection or data management. For example, if the group is looking to start data collection or is ready to use the dataset within a model, we can make recommendations on how curation principles can be applied to better document and steward the data.</li>
  <li>The dataset(s) can be of <strong>any modality</strong> and regarding <strong>any domain</strong>.</li>
  <li>The dataset(s) can be <strong>new or already existing</strong>. For example, if the 
ML group often uses existing datasets, we can evaluate datasets using the framework to inform their selection of which datasets to reuse.</li>
</ul>

<p><u>Expected Activities and Outcomes:</u> 
The findings from this study would result in <strong>1) improved joint understanding of the benefits resulting from data curation, 2) tailored insights for the team’s curation processes, and 3) deepened cross-disciplinary scholarship</strong>. The project 
would thus provide insights on practical approaches in performing and adopting data curation practices that result in improved datasets and consequently models.</p>

<p>Potential activities with the expected outcomes are listed below, this is not a comprehensive list and the activities will depend on the collaborative needs of the project.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Workshop to introduce data curation concepts</li>
  <li>Collaborative examination of current curation practices and proposal for improvements for data workflows</li>
  <li>Sample evaluations of dataset documentation for new datasets created by the ML team</li>
  <li>Sample evaluations of dataset documentation for existing datasets used by the ML team (or in consideration to be used)</li>
  <li>Examination of dataset(s) to glean usage to be applied for various ML efforts</li>
</ol>

<p>If you are interested, please contact Prof. Christoph Becker at <a href="mailto:christoph.becker@utoronto.ca">christoph.becker@utoronto.ca</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are looking to collaborate with a ML group (industry or academia) who wants to review and refine their data practices for improved documentation. Please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshop: Computing and AI Through the Lens of Degrowth</title><link href="/2025/03/01/jsd-degrowth-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshop: Computing and AI Through the Lens of Degrowth" /><published>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/03/01/jsd-degrowth-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/03/01/jsd-degrowth-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>JSD 2024-25 Workshop Series: Workshop 3</strong><br />
<strong>Online, March 21, 2025</strong><br />
Pre-session 9:30-10:00am ET<br />
Workshop 10:00am-12:00pm ET<br />
Stay and chat till 12:30pm ET</p>

<p>The Just Sustainability Design Lab at University of Toronto’s Faculty of Information 
invites you to join us for an online workshop session on “Computing and AI Through the Lens of Degrowth” 
on March 21, 2025 from 10am-12pm ET.</p>

<p>Degrowth is a coherent framework for reorganizing social and economic relations<sup>(1–4)</sup> that 
has significant implications for the role and meaning of technology development<sup>(5,6)</sup>, including in computing<sup>(7)</sup>. 
The field of computing is now beginning to grapple with degrowth and post-growth<sup>(8,9)</sup> perspectives (e.g. an upcoming 
<a href="https://pointed-waterlily-f95.notion.site/Advancing-Post-growth-HCI-15dec6ab184b809b8692ec6a3d578089">CHI workshop</a> 
and the <a href="https://computingwithinlimits.org/2025/">LIMITS workshops</a>).</p>

<p>In this informal workshop, we bring degrowth perspectives to bear on information technology and computing, 
including AI. We will briefly share recent research from the JSD lab on <em>Limits to AI Growth</em> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17980v1">(preprint)</a> and 
preliminary results on modelling the impact of AI <em>on</em> planetary Limits to Growth, then frame the conversation 
around ‘releasing technology from growth’ and open the discussion. We welcome further brief talks, lightning talks, 
or discussion prompts around the intersection of degrowth and computing.</p>

<p>The main purpose of this workshop is to foster a conversation about what it means to take a degrowth 
lens to computing and IT, including AI, and to make new connections between researchers who are 
interested in these questions.</p>

<p>Please register here for the workshop: <a href="https://forms.office.com/r/nhZ7tmNnnr">https://forms.office.com/r/nhZ7tmNnnr</a>.</p>

<p>The workshop itself is not an introduction to the framework of degrowth - we organize the 
conversation with the idea that everyone is familiar with it. But we will preface the main workshop 
session with a half-hour “Ask me Anything about Degrowth” session in which Christoph would do his best to 
respond to any questions you have. Please indicate your interest in attending the AMA, in the <a href="https://forms.office.com/r/nhZ7tmNnnr">registration form</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Agenda:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li><em>Optional:</em> AMA about degrowth (9:30-10:00am, Christoph)</li>
  <li>Workshop introduction (10:00-10:20am, Christoph)</li>
  <li>Research talks (4) and discussion (10:20-11:20am)
    <ul>
      <li>Limits to AI Growth (Eshta Bhardwaj)</li>
      <li>Impact of AI on Limits to Growth (Nara Guliyeva)</li>
      <li>Degrowth: Releasing Tech from Growth (Christoph Becker)</li>
      <li>Cooperative Approaches for Data Platforms (Nadia Mariyan Smith and Nils Bonfils)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Other research, lightning talks, discussion (11:20-11:45am)</li>
  <li>Wrap up: what’s next (11:45am-12:00pm)</li>
  <li><em>Optional:</em> Stay and chat (12:00-12:30pm)</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Eshta Bhardwaj:</strong> Eshta Bhardwaj is a PhD student at the Faculty of Information studying 
data practices in machine learning. Her research interests include examining how
techniques from data curation can improve data practices to increase accountability, transparency, and make ML model development more sustainable 
and resource-efficient. In this talk, she presents her 
recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17980v1">paper</a> which is a systemic analysis of the AI scaling landscape 
and its limiting factors (e.g., data availability) using the modelling constructs of system dynamics.</p>

<p><strong>Nara Guliyeva:</strong> Nara Guliyeva is currently a master’s student majoring in 
Human-Centered Data Science at the iSchool. She holds a Master’s degree from Columbia University and 
has worked at the United Nations Development Programme, focusing on innovation and sustainability. Her research explores how AI growth influence 
future-forward projections within the World3 Model, which examines long-term resource constraints, pioneered by the “The Limits to Growth” study. 
She investigates how AI-driven advancements—reliant on energy-intensive data centers, finite raw materials, and extensive financial investments—create feedback 
loops that may accelerate resource depletion and pollution. In this talk, she examines the role of AI growth in affecting World3 Model projections and invites 
discussion on incorporating AI-driven trends into World3 modeling.</p>

<p><strong>Christoph Becker:</strong> Christoph Becker is Full Professor at the Faculty of Information at the University of Toronto, where he leads the Just Sustainability Design lab, 
a Fellow of the SDG Scholars Academy at the University of Toronto, and a member of the School of the Environment. His transdisciplinary program of research in responsible 
computing helps enact meaningful and lasting change in computing research and practice to meet the urgent need for sustainability and social justice.</p>

<p><strong>Nadia Mariyan Smith:</strong> Nadia Mariyan Smith is a master’s student specializing in User Experience Design at the Faculty of Information. 
With a background in community work, they are interested in justice-oriented, more-than-human design approaches that emphasize collective well-being and ecological 
sustainability. In this talk, they will discuss a project they are working on with Christoph Becker and Nils Bonfils on determining the feasibility of a 
data platform cooperative for people living with diabetes.</p>

<p><strong>Nils Bonfils:</strong> Nils is a PhD student in the Department of Computer Science at UofT. 
His research interest lies at the intersection of Computer Science, STS and the Environment. His current research is about 
improving current data about historical flood events in the GTA by leveraging digital newspaper archives, furthermore this project allows 
him to think about different ways of understanding and representing data about floods. Exploring alterities has always been an important aspect of research for him.</p>

<p>References</p>

<ol>
  <li>Kallis, G., Paulson, S., D’Alisa, G. &amp; Demaria, F. <em>The Case for Degrowth.</em> (Polity, UK, 2020).</li>
  <li>Hickel, J. The anti-colonial politics of degrowth. <em>Polit. Geogr.</em> <strong>88</strong>, 102404 (2021).</li>
  <li>Hickel, J. What does degrowth mean? A few points of clarification. <em>Globalizations</em> <strong>18</strong>, 1105–1111 (2021). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/14747731.2020.1812222">https://doi.org/10.1080/14747731.2020.1812222</a></li>
  <li>Hickel, J. <em>Less Is More: How Degrowth Will Save the World.</em> (Penguin Random House, 2020).</li>
  <li>Pansera, M. &amp; Fressoli, M. Innovation without growth: Frameworks for understanding technological change in a post-growth era. <em>Organization</em> <strong>28</strong>, 380–404 (2021).</li>
  <li>Kostakis, V., Niaros, V. &amp; Giotitsas, C. Beyond global versus local: illuminating a cosmolocal framework for convivial technology development. <em>Sustain. Sci.</em> <strong>18</strong>, 2309–2322 (2023).</li>
  <li>Kwet, M. <em>Digital Degrowth: Technology in the Age of Survival.</em> (Pluto Press, London, 2024).</li>
  <li>Savini, F. Post-Growth, Degrowth, the Doughnut, and Circular Economy: A Short Guide for Policymakers. <em>J. City Clim. Policy Econ.</em> <strong>2</strong>, 113–123 (2024). <a href="https://jccpe.utpjournals.press/doi/full/10.3138/jccpe-2023-0004">https://jccpe.utpjournals.press/doi/full/10.3138/jccpe-2023-0004</a></li>
  <li>Kallis, G. <em>et al.</em> Post-growth: the science of wellbeing within planetary boundaries. <em>Lancet Planet. Health</em> <strong>9</strong>, e62–e78 (2025).</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="talk" /><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our lab is hosting an online open workshop session on Computing and AI Through the Lens of Degrowth on March 21, 2025, from 10:00 AM to 12:00 PM. Please see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Christoph appointed as SDG fellow!</title><link href="/2025/01/22/cb-sdgfellow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Christoph appointed as SDG fellow!" /><published>2025-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/01/22/cb-sdgfellow</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/01/22/cb-sdgfellow.html"><![CDATA[<p>Christoph was recently appointed as one of the new Fellows to the 
SDGs Scholars Academy. The Fellows contribute to driving SDG-related research. See more <a href="https://t.co/WKIog6TuFR">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Christoph was recently appointed as one of the new Fellows to the SDGs Scholars Academy, see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Paper: CSCW 2025</title><link href="/2025/01/13/cscw-han-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Paper: CSCW 2025" /><published>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/01/13/cscw-han-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/01/13/cscw-han-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p>In the densifying data ecosystem of today’s cities, 
data intermediaries are crucial stakeholders in facilitating data access and use. 
Community advocates live in these sites of social injustices and opportunities for change. 
Highly experienced in working with data to enact change, they offer distinctive insights on data practices and tools. 
This paper examines the unique perspectives that community advocates offer on data intermediaries. Based on interviews with 17 
advocates working with 23 grassroots and nonprofit organizations, we propose the quality of “near” and “far” to be seriously considered in 
data intermediaries’ works and articulate advocates’ vision of connecting “near data” and “far data.” To pursue this vision, 
we identified three pathways for data intermediaries: align data exploration with ways of storytelling, communicate context and 
uncertainties, and decenter artifacts for relationship building. These pathways help data intermediaries to put data feminism 
into practice, surface design opportunities and tensions, and raise key questions for supporting the pursuit of the Right to the City.</p>

<p>Please find the full paper <a href="/neardatafardata/CSCW2025_Near_Data_Far_Data_CameraReady.pdf">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="paper" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, 'Near Data' and 'Far Data' for Urban Sustainability: How Do Community Advocates Envision Data Intermediaries?, has been accepted to CSCW this year. See full post for the links to the paper.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Insolvent receives the Choice “Outstanding Academic Title” Award.</title><link href="/2025/01/03/insolvent-ala-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insolvent receives the Choice “Outstanding Academic Title” Award." /><published>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2025/01/03/insolvent-ala-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2025/01/03/insolvent-ala-award.html"><![CDATA[<p>Christoph’s book ‘INSOLVENT: How to Reorient Computing for Just Sustainability’ 
was selected as an ‘outstanding academic title’ for 2024 <a href="https://www.choice360.org/choice-pick/outstanding-academic-titles-2024/">by the ALA Choice</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Insolvent receives the Choice "Outstanding Academic Title" Award, see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research Assistant Job Posting</title><link href="/2024/12/18/RApost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Assistant Job Posting" /><published>2024-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/12/18/RApost</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/12/18/RApost.html"><![CDATA[<p>For a project on the <strong>environmental impact of AI</strong> at the Just Sustainability Design lab, we are seeking up to three RA positions immediately for the winter term.</p>

<p><strong>Compensation:</strong> Stipend or casual RA contract ($30+benefits/hr for MI students)</p>

<p><strong>Effort:</strong> about ~40-100h (some flexibility)</p>

<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Winter term, with a quick start in early January.</p>

<p><strong>Description:</strong></p>

<p>This project synthesizes what is known about the environmental impact of AI and related technologies and mobilizes this knowledge creatively. We are looking for students to help with a range of tasks including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>graphic poster design</li>
  <li>web design</li>
  <li>web development</li>
  <li>survey design and analysis</li>
  <li>project management and coordination</li>
  <li>literature reviews and synthesis</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Candidate Requirements:</strong></p>

<p>Any combination of the following:</p>
<ul>
  <li>awareness of and interest in the environmental impact of AI technologies</li>
  <li>proven design skills for print</li>
  <li>proven design skills for web</li>
  <li>web development</li>
  <li>survey design and analysis</li>
  <li>project management and coordination</li>
  <li>literature reviews and media monitoring</li>
  <li>social media / PR</li>
</ul>

<p>Interested candidates should contact Prof. Christoph Becker at <a href="mailto:christoph.becker@utoronto.ca">christoph.becker@utoronto.ca</a> with their CV/resume and a statement of interest right away. Applicants will be considered on a rolling basis.</p>

<p>If you have any questions, please reach out!</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For a project on the environmental impact of AI, we are seeking up to three RA positions immediately for the winter term.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NeurIPS Datasets and Benchmarks 2024</title><link href="/2024/11/16/neurips24.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NeurIPS Datasets and Benchmarks 2024" /><published>2024-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/11/16/neurips24</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/11/16/neurips24.html"><![CDATA[<p>Data curation is a field with origins in librarianship and archives, whose scholarship and thinking on data issues go back centuries, if not millennia. 
The field of machine learning is increasingly observing the importance of data curation to the advancement of both applications 
and fundamental understanding of machine learning models – evidenced not least by the creation of the Datasets and Benchmarks track itself. 
Our work provides an analysis of recent dataset development practices at NeurIPS through the lens of data curation. 
We present an evaluation framework for dataset documentation, consisting of a rubric and toolkit developed through a thorough 
literature review of data curation principles. We use the framework to systematically assess the strengths and weaknesses in 
current dataset development practices of 60 datasets published in the NeurIPS Datasets and Benchmarks track from 2021-2023. 
Our results indicate greater need for documentation about environmental footprint, ethical 
considerations, and data management. In this work, we suggest targeted strategies and resources to improve documentation in these areas and 
provide recommendations for the NeurIPS peer-review process that prioritize rigorous data curation in ML.</p>

<p>It was accepted at The Thirty-Eighth Annual Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Datasets &amp; Benchmarks track as a spotlight poster. 
The paper can be found <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22473">here</a> and the recorded talk 
is available on <a href="https://youtu.be/uLsfFjbERAI">YouTube</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="paper" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, The State of Data Curation at NeurIPS: An Assessment of Dataset Development Practices in the Datasets and Benchmarks Track, has been accepted in the NeurIPS Datasets & Benchmarks track. See full post for the links to the paper and recorded talk.]]></summary></entry></feed>