<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-18T21:01:44+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Just Sustainability Design</title><entry><title type="html">Funded PhD student positions for 2025</title><link href="/2024/10/10/newphdpositions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Funded PhD student positions for 2025" /><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/10/10/newphdpositions</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/10/10/newphdpositions.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Faculty of Information at UofT offers fully funded PhD student positions to study with me in the areas of HCI, IT for sustainability, 
Civic Tech, CSCW, Computing within Limits, ethical &amp; responsible tech, alternative AI, &amp; related areas. Deadline: Dec. 1 for Fall 2025 start.</p>

<p>Come join the Just Sustainability Design Lab! <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/lab/">https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/lab/</a></p>

<figure class="figure">
  <a class="figure-image" aria-label="figure link">
    <img src="/images/phdpositionsatjsd.jpg" style="
        width: 60%;
        max-height: unset;
      " alt="figure image" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />
  </a>
  
</figure>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Faculty of Information at UofT offers fully funded PhD student positions to study with me - Come join the Just Sustainability Design Lab! See full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshop: Sustainable Neighbourhoods, Sustainable Cities</title><link href="/2024/10/09/new-dci-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshop: Sustainable Neighbourhoods, Sustainable Cities" /><published>2024-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/10/09/new-dci-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/10/09/new-dci-workshop.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Just Sustainability Design Lab at the University of Toronto’s Faculty of Information 
invites you to join us for an online open workshop session on Sustainable Neighborhoods, Sustainable Cities on October 21, 2024, from 12:30 PM to 2:30 PM.</p>

<p>In this workshop, we will showcase past and ongoing research projects from the lab, 
including designing urban sustainability data exploration tools, addressing psychological distance through design, 
and examining the data practices of urban sustainability advocacy groups in Toronto.</p>

<p>We are also excited to welcome Yifan Kong, a PhD candidate from the University of Sydney’s 
Games and Play Lab, who will present her research on storytelling, cultural heritage, and human-computer interaction.</p>

<p>We encourage participants to share their own ongoing research through 5-minute lightning talks, followed by a collaborative feedback session.</p>

<p>Register here: <a href="https://forms.office.com/r/cRh93N4hZd">https://forms.office.com/r/cRh93N4hZd</a></p>

<p>We look forward to your participation!</p>

<figure class="figure">
  <a class="figure-image" aria-label="figure link">
    <img src="/images/JSDWorkshopPoster.png" style="
        width: 60%;
        max-height: unset;
      " alt="figure image" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />
  </a>
  
</figure>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="talk" /><category term="event" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our lab, the Just Sustainability Design Lab is hosting an online open workshop session on Sustainable Neighborhoods, Sustainable Cities on October 21, 2024, from 12:30 PM to 2:30 PM. Please see full post for details.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/JSDWorkshopPoster.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/JSDWorkshopPoster.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insolvent reviewed in Journal of Responsible Technology</title><link href="/2024/10/01/insolvent-review-jrt.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insolvent reviewed in Journal of Responsible Technology" /><published>2024-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/10/01/insolvent-review-jrt</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/10/01/insolvent-review-jrt.html"><![CDATA[<p>Christoph’s book “Insolvent” was reviewed at length in the Journal of Responsible Technology by a very capable team of researchers. 
Their conclusion: “Overall, Insolvent renders great service to the social sciences’ understanding of computing as an important science and technology and articulates a fierce reflexive critique of computer science from within the field”</p>

<p>Read their extended analysis <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jrt.2024.100092">here</a>!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Insolvent was reviewed in the Journal of Responsible Technology, see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Talk at the AI and the Planet in Crisis Conference</title><link href="/2024/09/25/aiincrisis-talk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talk at the AI and the Planet in Crisis Conference" /><published>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/09/25/aiincrisis-talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/09/25/aiincrisis-talk.html"><![CDATA[<p>Christoph recently gave a talk at the <a href="https://philtech.univie.ac.at/ai-and-the-planet-in-crisis-conference/">AI and the Planet in Crisis Conference</a>. 
His <a href="https://philtech.univie.ac.at/ai-and-the-planet-in-crisis-conference/abstracts/christoph-becker/">talk</a> takes a systemic view to offer directions on how AI development 
should be organized and evaluated under the changing conditions of a world after expansion.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Christoph gave a talk about how to decouple AI innovation from expansion in a world after growth, see full post for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to our new visiting student!</title><link href="/2024/09/04/welcome-syed.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to our new visiting student!" /><published>2024-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/09/04/welcome-syed</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/09/04/welcome-syed.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are welcoming a new visiting student - Syed Ashfaq Hussain! He is a PhD candidate and research associate at the chair of Architectural Informatics at Technical University of Munich (TUM), Germany.
His research investigations include research data management policy design, requirement analysis, and system development.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are welcoming a new visiting student - Syed Ashfaq Hussain!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Eshta on a successful QE!</title><link href="/2024/08/01/eshta-qe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Eshta on a successful QE!" /><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/08/01/eshta-qe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/08/01/eshta-qe.html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations to Eshta Bhardwaj for a successful Qualifying Exam! See what Eshta’s working on next <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/members/eshta-bhardwaj.html">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations to Eshta Bhardwaj for a successful Qualifying Exam!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Han on a successful QE!</title><link href="/2024/06/21/han-qe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Han on a successful QE!" /><published>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/21/han-qe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/21/han-qe.html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations to Han Qiao for a successful Qualifying Exam! See what Han’s working on next <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/members/han-qiao.html">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations to Han Qiao for a successful Qualifying Exam!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LIMITS 2024</title><link href="/2024/06/18/limits-pd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LIMITS 2024" /><published>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/18/limits-pd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/18/limits-pd.html"><![CDATA[<p>Policy decisions relevant to the environment rely on tools like dashboards to provide information and data visualizations that enable decision-makers to make tradeoffs. 
Because all outcomes from policies relevant to climate change occur at a distance, decision-makers experience so-called ‘psychological distance’ to environmental decisions in terms of space, time, 
social identity, and hypotheticality. Since policy decisions to achieve a safe planetary space are urgently needed for immediate transition, we need a design practice that takes into account how 
psychological distance affects cognition and decision-making. Our paper explores the role of alternative design approaches in developing visualizations used for climate policymaking. Our paper 
lays out how future research on the impacts of alternative design approaches on psychological distance can make data used for policy decisions more tangible and visceral. In the paper, we synthesize 
literature from environmental psychology and social and cognitive psychology to explore how the design of decision tools can leverage approaches like speculative design and data visceralization to invoke 
affective responses to environmental decisions to help traverse psychological distance. It was accepted at the Tenth 
Workshop on Computing within Limits (LIMITS 2024). The paper can be found <a href="https://computingwithinlimits.org/2024/papers/limits2024-bhardwaj-psychological-distance.pdf">here</a> and the recorded talk 
is available on <a href="https://youtu.be/emIIKWG12YM">YouTube</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="paper" /><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, Limits at a Distance: Design Directions to Address Psychological Distance in Policy Decisions, has been accepted at the Tenth Computing Within Limits Workshop. See full post for the links to the paper and recorded talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FAccT 2024</title><link href="/2024/06/03/facct-dcml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAccT 2024" /><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/03/facct-dcml</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/03/facct-dcml.html"><![CDATA[<p>Studies of dataset development in machine learning call for greater attention to the data practices 
that make model development possible and shape its outcomes. Many argue that the adoption of theory 
and practices from archives and data curation fields can support greater fairness, accountability, 
transparency, and more ethical machine learning.</p>

<p>In response, we are examining data practices in machine learning dataset development through the 
lens of data curation. We evaluate data practices in machine learning <strong>as data curation practices</strong>.</p>

<p>For our first paper on this topic, “Machine Learning Data Practices through a Data Curation Lens: 
An Evaluation Framework”, we evaluated data practices in machine learning as data curation practices. 
We developed an evaluation rubric and applied it to a sample of NeurIPS papers to see 
what we would find. It was accepted at the ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and 
Transparency (ACM FAccT 2024).</p>

<p>The 12 minute talk is available on <a href="https://youtu.be/C5VwJBE31JY?si=lFynqavsAiL8tPpF">YouTube</a>. 
The paper can be read <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3630106.3658955">here</a>.</p>

<p>To evaluate data practices in machine learning as data curation practices, 
we developed a framework for evaluating machine learning datasets using data curation 
concepts and principles through a rubric. Through a mixed-methods analysis of evaluation results 
for 25 ML datasets, we study the feasibility of data curation principles to be adopted for machine 
learning data work in practice and explore how data curation is currently performed. We find that 
researchers in machine learning, which often emphasizes model development, struggle to apply 
standard data curation principles. Our findings illustrate difficulties at the intersection of 
these fields, such as evaluating dimensions that have shared terms in both fields but non-shared 
meanings, a high degree of interpretative flexibility in adapting concepts without 
prescriptive restrictions, obstacles in limiting the depth of data curation expertise needed to 
apply the rubric, and challenges in scoping the extent of documentation dataset creators are 
responsible for. We propose ways to address these challenges and develop an overall framework 
for evaluation that outlines how data curation concepts and methods can inform machine learning 
data practices.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="paper" /><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, Machine Learning Data Practices through a Data Curation Lens: An Evaluation Framework, has been accepted at the ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAccT 2024). See full post for the links to the paper and recorded talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Insolvent receives PROSE Award Finalist selection for Engineering and Technology.</title><link href="/2024/03/10/prose-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insolvent receives PROSE Award Finalist selection for Engineering and Technology." /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/03/10/prose-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/03/10/prose-award.html"><![CDATA[<p>My book ‘INSOLVENT: How to Reorient Computing for Just Sustainability’ is a finalist in the PROSE Awards in the Engineering and Technology category :raised_hands:! If you missed it, it’s still <a href="https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/5594/InsolventHow-to-Reorient-Computing-for-Just">open access</a>. You can find more information about the book <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/insolvent/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My book ‘INSOLVENT: How to Reorient Computing for Just Sustainability’ is a finalist in the PROSE Awards in the Engineering and Technology category :raised_hands:! If you missed it, it’s still open access. You can find more information about the book here.]]></summary></entry></feed>