<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-17T12:45:01+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Just Sustainability Design</title><entry><title type="html">Congrats to Han on a successful QE!</title><link href="/2024/06/21/han-qe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Congrats to Han on a successful QE!" /><published>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/21/han-qe</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/21/han-qe.html"><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations to Han Qiao for a successful Qualifying Exam! See what Han’s working on next <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/members/han-qiao.html">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Congratulations to Han Qiao for a successful Qualifying Exam!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LIMITS 2024</title><link href="/2024/06/18/limits-pd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LIMITS 2024" /><published>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/18/limits-pd</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/18/limits-pd.html"><![CDATA[<p>Policy decisions relevant to the environment rely on tools like dashboards to provide information and data visualizations that enable decision-makers to make tradeoffs. 
Because all outcomes from policies relevant to climate change occur at a distance, decision-makers experience so-called ‘psychological distance’ to environmental decisions in terms of space, time, 
social identity, and hypotheticality. Since policy decisions to achieve a safe planetary space are urgently needed for immediate transition, we need a design practice that takes into account how 
psychological distance affects cognition and decision-making. Our paper explores the role of alternative design approaches in developing visualizations used for climate policymaking. Our paper 
lays out how future research on the impacts of alternative design approaches on psychological distance can make data used for policy decisions more tangible and visceral. In the paper, we synthesize 
literature from environmental psychology and social and cognitive psychology to explore how the design of decision tools can leverage approaches like speculative design and data visceralization to invoke 
affective responses to environmental decisions to help traverse psychological distance. It was accepted at the Tenth 
Workshop on Computing within Limits (LIMITS 2024). The paper can be found <a href="https://computingwithinlimits.org/2024/papers/limits2024-bhardwaj-psychological-distance.pdf">here</a> and the recorded talk 
is available on <a href="https://youtu.be/emIIKWG12YM">YouTube</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="paper" /><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, Limits at a Distance: Design Directions to Address Psychological Distance in Policy Decisions, has been accepted at the Tenth Computing Within Limits Workshop. See full post for the links to the final paper and recorded talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FAccT 2024</title><link href="/2024/06/03/facct-dcml.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAccT 2024" /><published>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/06/03/facct-dcml</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/06/03/facct-dcml.html"><![CDATA[<p>Studies of dataset development in machine learning call for greater attention to the data practices 
that make model development possible and shape its outcomes. Many argue that the adoption of theory 
and practices from archives and data curation fields can support greater fairness, accountability, 
transparency, and more ethical machine learning.</p>

<p>In response, we are examining data practices in machine learning dataset development through the 
lens of data curation. We evaluate data practices in machine learning <strong>as data curation practices</strong>.</p>

<p>For our first paper on this topic, “Machine Learning Data Practices through a Data Curation Lens: 
An Evaluation Framework”, we evaluated data practices in machine learning as data curation practices. 
We developed an evaluation rubric and applied it to a sample of NeurIPS papers to see 
what we would find. It was accepted at the ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and 
Transparency (ACM FAccT 2024).</p>

<p>The 12 minute talk is available on <a href="https://youtu.be/C5VwJBE31JY?si=lFynqavsAiL8tPpF">YouTube</a>. 
The paper can be read <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3630106.3658955">here</a>.</p>

<p>To evaluate data practices in machine learning as data curation practices, 
we developed a framework for evaluating machine learning datasets using data curation 
concepts and principles through a rubric. Through a mixed-methods analysis of evaluation results 
for 25 ML datasets, we study the feasibility of data curation principles to be adopted for machine 
learning data work in practice and explore how data curation is currently performed. We find that 
researchers in machine learning, which often emphasizes model development, struggle to apply 
standard data curation principles. Our findings illustrate difficulties at the intersection of 
these fields, such as evaluating dimensions that have shared terms in both fields but non-shared 
meanings, a high degree of interpretative flexibility in adapting concepts without 
prescriptive restrictions, obstacles in limiting the depth of data curation expertise needed to 
apply the rubric, and challenges in scoping the extent of documentation dataset creators are 
responsible for. We propose ways to address these challenges and develop an overall framework 
for evaluation that outlines how data curation concepts and methods can inform machine learning 
data practices.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="paper" /><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, Machine Learning Data Practices through a Data Curation Lens: An Evaluation Framework, has been accepted at the ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAccT 2024). See full post for the links to the final paper and recorded talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Insolvent receives PROSE Award Finalist selection for Engineering and Technology.</title><link href="/2024/03/10/prose-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insolvent receives PROSE Award Finalist selection for Engineering and Technology." /><published>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/03/10/prose-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/03/10/prose-award.html"><![CDATA[<p>My book ‘INSOLVENT: How to Reorient Computing for Just Sustainability’ is a finalist in the PROSE Awards in the Engineering and Technology category :raised_hands:! If you missed it, it’s still <a href="https://direct.mit.edu/books/oa-monograph/5594/InsolventHow-to-Reorient-Computing-for-Just">open access</a>. You can find more information about the book <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/insolvent/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My book ‘INSOLVENT: How to Reorient Computing for Just Sustainability’ is a finalist in the PROSE Awards in the Engineering and Technology category :raised_hands:! If you missed it, it’s still open access. You can find more information about the book here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to our new lab members!</title><link href="/2024/01/10/new-lab-members.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to our new lab members!" /><published>2024-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/10/new-lab-members</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/10/new-lab-members.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are welcoming two new lab members - <a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/members/monica-iqbal.html">Monica Iqbal</a> and 
<a href="https://justsustainabilitydesign.org/members/matt-oreilly.html">Matt O’Reilly</a>! Please visit their profile pages to learn about their research projects and interests.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are welcoming two new lab members - Monica Iqbal and Matt O'Reilly!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research Assistant Job Posting</title><link href="/2023/11/14/dcml-ra-jobpost.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Assistant Job Posting" /><published>2023-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/11/14/dcml-ra-jobpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/11/14/dcml-ra-jobpost.html"><![CDATA[<p>For an evaluation of data curation in machine learning, conducted by Eshta Bhardwaj, Christoph Becker, and Tegan Rajkumar-Maharaj, we are seeking up to four RA positions immediately, for the coming months.</p>

<p><strong>Compensation:</strong> Stipend or casual RA contract ($35/hr)</p>

<p><strong>Effort:</strong> about ~50-100h (some flexibility)</p>

<p><strong>Timeline:</strong> Stage 1 is time sensitive, to be completed by mid December (&lt;20 hours). Stage 2 is more flexible and will take place in the first half of winter term.</p>

<p><strong>Description:</strong>
Our study evaluates existing dataset development processes within machine learning research and develops a method for increasing transparency and improving the documentation of dataset development.</p>

<p>We are looking for 2-4 individuals with a research background in fields related to machine learning, data science, or computer science, who are interested in taking a closer look into the data sets used in machine learning and examine their documentation.
You will learn about data curation in machine learning and its role in fairness, bias, and accountability. You will review, classify, and evaluate datasets and their documentation from published research in a machine learning conference. 
Successful candidates will be invited to become co-authors of the resulting research paper(s).</p>

<p><strong>Candidate Requirements:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Must be familiar with and comfortable reading machine learning research papers</li>
  <li>Has a background in machine learning, data science, or computer science</li>
  <li>Preferred: Good knowledge of benchmarking in ML</li>
  <li>Preferred: Current graduate student in a field related to the study</li>
</ul>

<p>Interested candidates should contact Prof. Christoph Becker at <a href="mailto:christoph.becker@utoronto.ca">christoph.becker@utoronto.ca</a> with their CV/resume and a statement of interest right away.
Applicants will be considered on a rolling basis.</p>]]></content><author><name>christoph-becker</name></author><category term="closed" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For an evaluation of data curation in machine learning, conducted by Eshta Bhardwaj, Christoph Becker, and Tegan Rajkumar-Maharaj, we are seeking up to four RA positions immediately, for the coming months.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Curbcut Toronto Launch</title><link href="/2023/06/28/curbcut-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curbcut Toronto Launch" /><published>2023-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/06/28/curbcut-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/06/28/curbcut-launch.html"><![CDATA[<p>An overview, introduction and demo of <a href="https://toronto.curbcut.ca/">Curbcut Toronto</a>, recorded at the DCI launch event in June 2023.
The recording can be found on <a href="https://youtu.be/hNwKTmo9WHA?si=QfEbFMtZXF1v9xRY">YouTube</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>eshta-bhardwaj</name></author><category term="talk" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to share the first look at Curbcut Toronto through a short workshop showcasing its map-based spatial and analytical features. See full post for the link to the recorded talk.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LIMITS 2023</title><link href="/2023/06/14/limits-curbcut.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LIMITS 2023" /><published>2023-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/06/14/limits-curbcut</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/06/14/limits-curbcut.html"><![CDATA[<p>Current computing methods addressing climate change employ open data platforms, interactive maps, and predictive modeling to support policy analysis, 
evaluate effects of policies, and support information access. These data exploration and analysis tools carry beautiful visions, including 
helping people better understand their cities, making communities’ challenges transparent, and facilitating systematic approaches to decision making 
for sustainability issues. They are also limited, and the reality they partake in turns out to be more nuanced. The tools that help us to get to know a city 
through data are never neutral but always an expression of politics and power dynamics. Data-driven decision-making also often produces biased, discriminatory, 
and unfair results that are difficult to trace and comprehend.</p>

<p>Our paper attends to five key tensions in this design space by demonstrating how design theories 
can reorient the design process for computing systems used in both top-down decision-making and bottom-up community effort. 
More specifically, we investigate how four design approaches (Social Design, Speculative Design, Feminist Data Practices, Design Justice) 
can be applied to a tool for empowering community efforts and informing decision-making for climate change. We illustrate this through an open-source 
map-based data platform aiming to support communities with sustainability data exploration and information sharing. We unfold the challenges and opportunities 
in designing during a climate crisis by translating design theories into concrete actions that prioritize community values.</p>

<p>The full paper can be found <a href="https://doi.org/10.21428/bf6fb269.541455de">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>han-qiao</name></author><category term="paper" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our paper, Pathways to urban sustainability: Design perspectives on a data curation and visualization platform, has been accepted at the Ninth Computing Within Limits Workshop (LIMITS 2023). See full post for the link to the final paper.]]></summary></entry></feed>